Guide to the Wakefield Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Wakefield Family Papers
1904-2000
RG 183
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of Arthur Paul Wakefield and family, including information regarding medical work in China and interactions with Chinese colleagues, among them Francis C. M. Wei. Arthur Paul Wakefield was a medical missionary serving in China under the Disciples of Christ and Episcopal mission agencies from 1905 to 1927. He served at Luchowfu Hospital in Anhwei province from 1912 to 1919 and at Boone College, Central ChristianUniversity in Wuchang from 1919 to 1927. Following his return from China, Wakefield was involved in public health and tuberculosis treatment in Maine and Massachusetts.
Wakefield, Arthur Paul
Bundy, Robert E.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Catharine Wakefield Ward.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Paul Wakefield was born in North Bloomfield, Ohio on October 5, 1878. He grew up in Hiram, Ohio where his father taught at Hiram College. Wakefield (known as Paul) graduated from Hiram College in 1900. In 1904 he received his M.D. from Rush Medical College and married Olive Catharine Lindsay. Olive was a 1901 graduate of Hiram College and the sister of poet Vachel Lindsay. The Wakefields had three surviving children: Vachel, Catharine, and Martha. Their second child, Mary Churchill Wakefield, died of scarlet fever at the age of nine,
while a student at the Shanghai American School.
Paul Wakefield was a medical missionary in China, first stationed in Nanking under the Foreign Missionary Society of the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ) from 1905 to 1912 and later serving in Luchowfu until 1919 and in Wuchang under the Episcopal American Church Mission from 1919-1927. He was decorated by the Chinese Red Cross for flood relief and dyke reconstruction work along the Yangtze River. Wakefield received a Master's degree from Bethany College in 1907 and was a Rockefeller Foundation Fellow at the Graduate School of Tropical Medicine at Harvard University in 1917.
At Boone College, an Episcopal institution in Wuchang that became part of Huachung, or Central China University, Wakefield was in charge of student health work from 1919 to 1927 and also taught courses. He aided in saving the university property when Wuchang was under seige by the Soviet-Nationalist army in 1926-1927. In October 1928 all missionaries in the Wuchang area were forced to leave because of political disruption.
The Wakefields settled in Massachusetts where Paul worked for several years with the Massachusetts Department of Public Health Chadwick Clinic. Dr. Chadwick, later Commissioner of Public Health for Massachusetts, founded this ten-year clinic to examine public school students throughout Massachusetts for evidence of early tuberculosis. The Chadwick Clinic made such a difference in discovery and treatment of early stage tuberculosis that various sanitoria for young people in Massachusetts were converted to care for the elderly. Paul Wakefield later became superintendent of the Central Maine Sanatorium and specialized in surgical procedures for tuberculosis. He spent his final years back with the Massachusetts Department of Public Health directing a statewide program for crippled children. Paul Wakefield died suddenly at age 63.
Scope and Contents
These papers complement other collections at the Yale Divinity Library, including the Robert and Gladys Bundy Papers, Record Group 141 (colleagues of the Wakefields at Boone) and the records of Huachung University held in the Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia, Record Group No. 11. Quite apart from the China-related material in this collection is its interesting documentation of the treatment of tuberculosis in the United States during the 1930s.
In the Family Correspondence of Series I, letters written by Paul Wakefield to Olive from 1926 to 1927 provide valuable commentary on the political and economic situation in China and at Boone College. The General Correspondence: China-Related of Series II also provides detailed reporting of the situation in China, the siege of Wuchang, and mission "politics", particularly in substantive letters with Wakefield's colleague Robert Bundy and Bishop Logan H. Roots. Paul Wakefield was a man of strong opinions who did not hesitate to express his views. Also of interest in Series II are numerous letters from Francis C. M. Wei (1881-1976), who was President of Huachung University (Central China) and a prominent figure in Christian higher education and theology in China. Wakefield continued to receive correspondence from China after his return to the States, including a substantive series of letters from Bishop A. H. Gilman dated 1939-1946. The Topically arranged section of Series II contains both letters and other documents that provide information about Wakefield's work at Luchowfu Hospital and the circumstances surrounding his resignation, the seige of Wuchang in the fall of 1926, the development of Boone College and Central China (Huachung) University, the Wakefield's vacation home in Kuling, and the Nanking Incident of 1927.
The Writings, Sermons, and Speeches of Paul Wakefield in Series V include documentation of the Siege of Wuchang, medical subjects such as tuberculosis treatment, and devotional material. Of particular interest in Series V are writings by Minnie Vautrin describing the refugee work at Ginling College in Nanking during 1937-1938, as well as reports and writings by Francis C. M. Wei.
Series VI, Personal Items and Memorabilia includes biographical material, letters of condolence following Paul Wakefield's untimely death, and materials related to a controversial interview of Wakefield by New York Times reporter Frederick Wells in June 1927.
The Collected Material: China-Related of Series VII contains valuable documentation of the American Church Mission (Episcopal) in China, including printed newsletters of the District of Hankow (1926-1949) and printed newsletters of the Districts of Anking and Shanghai. Three issues of The Magpie, a magazine published by the students of Central China University provide fascinating insight into the campus life and issues of concern during the 1924-1926 period.
The Wakefield Papers also include photographs of the Wakefields, their colleagues and surroundings in China and samples of newspapers of the era from China and Japan.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence
II. General Correspondence: China-Related
III. General Correspondence: Post-China Era
IV. Writings/Sermons/Speeches of APW
V. Writings of Others
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia
VII. Collected Material: China-Related
VIII. Collected Material: Post-China Era
IX. Photographs
X. Newspapers
Missions -- China; Wuchang (Hubei Sheng, China) -- Church history; Wakefield, Arthur Paul; Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China
- Family Correspondence, Series I
  - To Wakefield parents (photocopies), 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - To Wakefield parents (photocopies), 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - To Lindsay family, 1904-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Paul Wakefield (APW) to Olive Lindsay Wakefield (OLW), incl. re. siege of Wuchang, 1917-1926 Sep (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - APW to OLW, primarily from Wuchang, 1926 Oct, n.m. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - APW to OLW, from Wuchang, 1927 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - APW to OLW and family, from Wuchang, Hankow, 1927 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - APW to OLW, from Shanghai, Japan, Paris, London, 1927 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - APW to OLW, from Massachusetts, 1928 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - APW to OLW, primarily from Massachusetts, 1928 Mar-1929 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - APW to OLW and family, from MA, Maine, 1930-1937, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - APW to children, primarily from Wuchang, 1926 Feb- 1927 Feb (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - APW to children, from Wuchang, Hankow, Japan, 1927 Mar-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - APW to children, 1928 Jan-1930(?) Nov (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - APW to children, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Catherine (daughter) to APW, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous family letters, 1927-2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- General Correspondence: China Era, Series II
  - APW and OLW to others
    - APW to Robert Bundy, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - APW to Bishop Huston, 1927 Aug (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Circular letters (APW), 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letters of OLW to others, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters to/from others
    - Bundys to Wakefields, 1926 Feb, 1927 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Bundys to Wakefields, 1927 Aug, 1928 Nov (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bundys to Wakefields, 1929 Feb, 1929 Nov (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Bundys to Wakefields, 1930 Feb, 1944 Oct (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bundys to Wakefields, 1945 May, 1953 Oct (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bundys to Catherine and Paul Ward, 1931 Apr, 1945 Jun (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Bundys to Catherine and Paul Ward, 1945 Sep, 1968 Nov (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - From Bates - Barrett (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - From Bishop and Mrs. Gilson, 1927 Oct, 1934 Jun (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - From Guttery - Lawson (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - From Samuel Lil, 1928 Jan, 1948 May (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - From Lichtenbergers, 1925 Nov, 1963 Mar (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - From Lyon - Randall (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - To/from Bishop Roots, 1919 Nov, 1942 Oct (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - From Ross - Vittaly (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - To/from Harry Wakefield, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - From Walker - R. Wood (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - F.C. M. Wei to Wakefields, 1927 May, 1948 Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - F. C. M. Wei to Paul Ward, 1949 Oct, 1950 Oct (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - To/from Bishop John Wood, 1926 Dec, 1937 Aug (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Circular letters from others
    - Disciples of Christ missionaries, 1938 Oct, 1950 Sep (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Bishop Gilman, 1939 Mar, 1944 Jun (Box 3, Folder 43-45)
    - Henry Hodgkin, 1924 Dec, 1933 Sep (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Topically arranged correspondence and documents
    - Luchowfu Hospital, incl. re. APW's resignation and letters B - C (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Luchowful Hospital, letters C - T (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Wuchang, 1926 Sep (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
    - Central China University, 1919-1937 (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
    - Kuling, 1925-1940 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Kuling - school reunion, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Nanking, 1927, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Miscellaneous, 1927-1931 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- General Correspondence: Post China Era, Series III
  - Re. Central Maine Sanatorium, 1933-1976 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Re. APW's resignation from Central Maine Sanatorium, 1936 Jul (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Writings, Speeches, Sermons of APW, 1926-1927; Series IV
  - Incl. "Siege of Wuchang", 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Incl. "A Toast to our Daughters"; Commencement address (1932) (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Miscellaneous untitled writings (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - "The Most Unforgettable Man I Ever Met": speech to Springfield Laymen's meeting; "What's the Matter with China?"; Sermon on Jon 9:13-25, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Incl. "The Feet of Young Men"; "Boys Will Be Boys" (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous untitled writings (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Re. tuberculosis; Chadwick Clinic (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
  - Commencement address for Worcester State College; writings re. tuberculosis treatment (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Incl. paper for Maine Medical Society (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Radio addresses, 1938, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Re. crippled children (Box 4, Folder 70)
- Writings of Others, Series V
  - Incl. by Robert Bundy: "Wakefield of Wuchang", 1924-1926 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - By George Sokolsky: "Americans in China"; "What Matters in Missions" (Box 4, Folder 71a)
  - By Minnie Vautrin: "Sharing the Abundant Life in a Refugee Camp"; reports re. Ginling College, 1933, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - By Florence G. Tyler: "At Last - Nanking", 1938 Nov (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - By F. C. M. Wei: "Missions in this Age"; "Understanding Present Day China"; reports re. Central China University (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - By T. F. Tsiang: "China at War"; by Lowe Chuah-hua: "A Layman's Interpretation", 1943 Dec (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - By Mrs. Theodore Roosevelt, Jr. "Escape from Shanghai" (from Saturday Evening Post ), 1937 Oct (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - By unidentified missionary: "Christian Interests and the Communist State of China", 1949 Mar (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - By Martha Wakefield Falcone - notes re. F. C. M. Wei, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series VI
  - Biographical information (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Legal and financial documents, incl. will of APW (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Obituaries, letters of condolence re. death of APW (Box 5, Folder 80a)
  - Family letters re. future of OLW (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Arthur Paul Wakefield Medical Scholarship (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Legal and financial documents (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Diplomatic records and passports (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Programs, cards, etc. (Box 5, Folder 84a)
  - Material re.controversial interview with New York Times reporter Frederick Moore, 1927 Jun (Box 5, Folder 85)
- Collected Material re. China, Series VII
  - Kuling Estate - directories and reports, 1930-1934 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Missions affairs: American Church Mission (Episcopal) in China; see Series II for additional documents related to Boone College, Central China University, 1923-1927 (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Missions affairs: Report of the Commission of the Department of Missions to Confer with Bishops of China, 1927 or 1928 (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Various reports from other missions in China, 1925, 1927, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1926 Oct, 1928 Dec (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1929 Feb, 1930 Dec (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1931 Jan, 1932 Dec (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1933 Jan, 1934 Oct (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1935 Jan, 1936 Nov (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - District of Hankow Newsletters, 1937 Feb - 1947 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Assorted pamphlets re. China, 1925-1927 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Assorted pamphlets re. China, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Pamphlet: "The Soviet in China Unmasked", 1927 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Pamphlet: "The Commission to the Far East", 1914 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Pamphlet: "Report of the Commission on Extra-Territoriality in China", 1926 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Magpie - student publication of Central China University, 1924 Dec, 1925 Apr (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Magpie - student publication of Central China University, 1926 Jun (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - The Cathedral Quarterly, 1935 Apr, 1938 Jan (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - China Primer; Chinese Christian Education, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - China Christian Newsletters, 1928 Mar, 1929 Mar (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - District of Anking Newsletters, 1926 May - 1928 Feb (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - District of Shanghai Newsletters, 1918 Jun, 1928 Apr (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - United Christian Missionary Society newsletters, 1927 Mar, 1928 Jan (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Nanking Bulletins, 1926 Sep, 1927 Mar (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Pamphlet: "June Twenty-third" - investigation of the Shakee Massacre, 1925 Jun (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - American Church Mission - List of missionaries, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - American Church Mission - Rules of the Mission, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Luchowfu Christian Hospital - annual reports (see also Series II), 1926, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Newsletter of the Chinese Students Christian Union, 1929 Mar (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - "The China Colleges", 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - "United China Relief News", 1943 Nov, 1944 Aug (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - American Friends Service Committee programs in China, 1947 Aug (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Newsclippings re. China, 1929- (Box 6, Folder 114a)
- Collected Material - Post China, 1928-1930; Series VIII
  - Re. tuberculosis work in Massachusetts, 1928-1930 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Central Maine Sanatorium - policies, reports, finances, 1932-ca.1936 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - "Pendle Hill - A Quaker Experiment" (Box 6, Folder 117)
- Photographs, Series IX
  - Kuling - groups and scenery (Box OV1, Folder 118)
  - Miscellaneous - China (Box OV1, Folder 119)
  - Missionaries to China (Box OV1, Folder 120)
  - Francis Wei family and clergy group (Box OV1, Folder 121)
  - Student groups (Box OV1, Folder 122)
  - Staff of Boone Middle School; Staff of Church General Hospital, Wuchang (Box OV1, Folder 123)
  - Glass plate - APW and banner procession (Box OV1, Folder 124)
  - Siege of Wuchang, 1926 Sep-Oct (Box OV1, Folder 124A)
  - Party at Consulate in Wuhu, ca.1911 (Box OV1, Folder 124B)
- Newspapers, Series X
  - Japan Advertiser, 1927 Mar 11, 12, Apr 10, 14 (Box OV1, Folder 125)
  - Shanghai Evening Post, 1943 Jan 8 (Box OV1, Folder 126)
  - Shanghai Evening Post, 1923 Jun 22 (Box OV1, Folder 126)
  - Peking and Tientsin Times, 1925 Aug 18,19, Sep 24, 25, Oct 1 (Box OV1, Folder 127)
  - Hankow Herald, 1925 Aug 30, Oct 8, 1927 Feb 27, Mar 22 (Box OV1, Folder 128)
  - North China Herald, 1927 Dec 8 (Box OV1, Folder 128)
  - The People Tribune, 1927 Jul 21 (Box OV1, Folder 128)
  - New York Times, 1928 Nov 25 (Box OV1, Folder 129)
  - Boston Herald, 1930 Jan 12, 19 (Box OV1, Folder 129)
  - Clippings from Japan Advertiser, 1927 Feb, Mar, Sep (Box OV1, Folder 130)
  - Independent Herald - Hankow re. Hankow riot, 1925 Jun (Box OV1, Folder 131)
  - Clippings - "Light on the Situation", 1925 (Box OV1, Folder 132)